<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-07-13T20:37:56+05:30</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">yama(यम) and viloma pranaayama(विलोम प्राणायम)</title><link href="/2020/07/13/YogaKshema-yama-and-viloma-pranayama.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="yama(यम) and viloma pranaayama(विलोम प्राणायम)" /><published>2020-07-13T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-07-13T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/2020/07/13/YogaKshema-yama-and-viloma-pranayama</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/07/13/YogaKshema-yama-and-viloma-pranayama.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;practice&quot;&gt;Practice&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;With the standard lying back with legs close to the bottom posture, loosen the major muscles of gluteus and thighs; and minor muscles of calf and foot; and warm the knees.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rotate the trunk with left hand against the knee and right hand behind the back on fingers. Repeat on the symmetric counterpart.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Standing up without taking support of the hands. There are five ways with ordering of graded difficulty
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;put the hands forward and lift&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;lift the hands and lift&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;forward fold the hands and lift&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;backward fold the hands with palms near bottom and lift&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;backward fold the hands with palms at chest line and lift&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;These five standing practices are interleaved with the five principles of yama outlined below in theory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;pranayama&quot;&gt;Pranayama&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A new way of breathing called Viloma. Viloma is a variant of abdominal diaphragmic breathing where inhalation is in 3 stages
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;first stage activates the lower abdominal muscles near the pelvis&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;second stage activates the middle muscles&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;third stage activates the upper muscles&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The exhalation reverses the process with
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;first stage contracting the upper muscles&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;second stage contracting the middle muscles&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;third stage contracting the lower muscles&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;theory&quot;&gt;Theory&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yoga is not about simply doing asanas and breathing. Its a holistic approach for betterment of personality and simultaneously the society. For this, sage Patanjali gave the Ashtanga Yoga Sutras. The first tenet of this sutras is the concept of Yama. Yama means “Donts”. There are five donts
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ahimsa (अहिंसा) : Non-violence of type physical, mental&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Satya (सत्य) : Truth&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Asteya (अस्तेय) : Non stealing of type physical, intellectual&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Brahmacharya (ब्रह्मचर्य) : Avoiding excess indulgence in sensual pleasures&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Aparigraha (अपरिग्रह) : Avoid greed; Minimizing acquiring essential things and avoiding acquiring non-essential things.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>fubar</name></author><category term="yoga" /><summary type="html">Yama is the first tenet of Ashtanga Yoga Sutra (अष्टांग योग सूत्र).The five subtenets of yama tenet are dileneated. Followed by the viloma pranayama</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">sitting Setubandhaasana (सेतुबंधासन) and posture correction Asanas</title><link href="/2020/07/10/YogaKshema-Setu-Bandhaasana.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="sitting Setubandhaasana (सेतुबंधासन) and posture correction Asanas" /><published>2020-07-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-07-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/2020/07/10/YogaKshema-Setu-Bandhaasana</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/07/10/YogaKshema-Setu-Bandhaasana.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;asanas&quot;&gt;Asanas&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Setubandhaasana: In the laid back with feet clamped to the bottom posture, Chin touching the chest lift the bottom up. Excellent for lower back, abdominal region and pelvis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In Swastikasana (Sitting posture), for &lt;strong&gt;postural correction&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Lift arms up and back of the body plane.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Place palms behind the back and lift chest and stretch neck behind the back and feel the tension in the neck.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;pranayama&quot;&gt;prAnAyama&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Revisit thoracic breathing, lungs open from base to apex, ribs should open up like umbrella.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>fubar</name></author><category term="yoga" /></entry><entry><title type="html">standing asanas and kapAlabhAti(कपालभाती) prAnAyama(प्राणायम)</title><link href="/2020/07/10/YogaKshema-kapalabhati.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="standing asanas and kapAlabhAti(कपालभाती) prAnAyama(प्राणायम)" /><published>2020-07-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-07-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/2020/07/10/YogaKshema-kapalabhati</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/07/10/YogaKshema-kapalabhati.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;asanas&quot;&gt;asanas&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After initial stretching exercises, get to standing posture.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;TAdAsana (ताडासन) : Standing posture&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Side stretching : Extend the arms along shoulder line &lt;strong&gt;keeping in mind not&lt;/strong&gt; to stretch the shoulder girdle. Rotate from the waist by 90 degrees clockwise and counter clockwise&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Side bending: Keep the arms touching the trunk and drag the palms downwards. Repeat other side.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Backward bending: Place the palms on waist with thumbs on the backbone. Mindful of the navel and chest center, extend them outwards while bending backward &lt;strong&gt;during the exhaling&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;pranayama&quot;&gt;prAnAyama&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;kapAlabhAti is a variant of abdominal diaphragmic breathing where there is conscious contraction of the abdominal muscles during exhalation followed by restoring relaxation of the muscles leading to “automatic” inhalation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As a &lt;strong&gt;subtle breathing technique&lt;/strong&gt;, which needs mastery, it is &lt;strong&gt;important&lt;/strong&gt; to not overdo the contraction as well as frequency of breathing should be manageable without much exertion and the number of repititions not exceeding 20 in the initial stages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>fubar</name></author><category term="yoga" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Assessing Research – An article by Prof. Desiraju</title><link href="/2020/07/09/assessing-research-by-prof-desiraju.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Assessing Research -- An article by Prof. Desiraju" /><published>2020-07-09T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-07-09T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/2020/07/09/assessing-research-by-prof-desiraju</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/07/09/assessing-research-by-prof-desiraju.html">&lt;p&gt;Below is the except of the commentary by Prof. Desiraju on the pitfalls of current evaluation procedures by policy makers to judge the quality of research output written on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/gautamdesiraju/posts/925803417847661?notif_id=1594149348660696&amp;amp;notif_t=nf_status_story&amp;amp;ref=notif&quot;&gt;Facebook post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Here is the text copy of my recent comment in Current Science
 co-authored with Bhushan Patwardhan
 on impact factors, h-index, and pirated journals University Grants commission
COMMENTARY (25th June 2020 issue)
Assessing research. The slippery slope.
Bhushan Patwardhan, University Grants Commission, New Delhi
Gautam R. Desiraju, Indian Institute of Science, Bengaluru
With the inevitable push towards better assessment of academics, new quantitative parameters have emerged such as the h-index, which is a measure of how many times an academic, typically a scientist, is cited by others in the field, and the Impact Factor (IF) of a journal, which is roughly an equivalent measure for the publishing medium itself. These numbers are a bit like retweets and ‘likes’ in Twitter. How many people like you and how many followers do you have? Isn’t it unfair that those with more followers get more retweets and ‘likes’ for putting out more or less the same kind of material?
The quantification of research output through bibliometrics has become de rigeur worldwide, often even substituting for qualitative assessments that can, supposedly become subjective and therefore whimsical. However, h-indices and IFs, while they may be precise in one way, need not always be accurate with respect to judging the importance of a researcher’s work.
The University Grants Commission (UGC) and the government science departments (DST, DBT) have been rightly concerned with the proper use of these parameters, noting as it were, their application to schemes of promotions, funding and recognitions in several countries. UGC also uses a simpler quantitative measure, namely the number of publications of a scientist, as a rigorous criterion for appointment and certification as a research supervisor.
Regulatory actions by the UGC and the science departments, while undertaken with the best possible intentions, have led to at least two unfortunate consequences in the Indian context.
The first concerns careless application of bibliometrics while deciding appointments, promotions and awards. Research points to things that are not visible. Research is not about repeating what is obvious. Just doing incremental things, merely extending what has been said and done, does not constitute meaningful research. You may receive a publication from such work, but you can be sure it is not going to be impactful or with long-lasting influence.
There is now the distressing trend of appointing and rewarding people merely because they have publications in high IF journals.
A pedestrian ‘follower’ paper from India can appear in a high IF journal for various reasons, including but not limited to the patronage sometimes extended by a First World referee towards an author from the Global South, a sense of noblesse oblige as it were, or a tendency to ‘allow’ an Indian follower in the same field to publish in a high IF journal if he/she cites a big ‘leader’ scientist from the First World. Such a ‘leader’ may well be the referee; the Indian paper gets published but it is never cited. Such ‘follower’ papers from the Global South will not be cited where it really matters.
Indian committees for appointments, assessments or awards at the central government level often go, sadly enough, by IFs of the publication journals of candidates. These committees are necessarily of a general composition. They cannot be expected to go into the finer but more crucial details of the candidates’ research. And here’s the rub: the devil is in these details and it is only this devil that can discriminate between truly insightful and adequately competent work. It’s not a surprise therefore that average academics get elevated to positions of authority in India because it is normally only the receipt of such awards that elevates one to such positions.
This anomaly concerns researchers at the higher end of the research spectrum. Let us now consider the second distressing consequence of using bibliometrics, but this time at the lower end.
Policy makers and administrators worldwide have been concerned for some time that research is being paid for twice over: the first time when it is funded and the second time when journal subscriptions are paid. Scientists should not be charged twice: once to undertake research and then to view the outcomes of that research. This has led to the appearance of a new type of journal, namely the Open Access (OA) publication. In an OA journal, an author pays a one-time fee to publish a paper. Subsequently, its access is open to anyone. So if a government funding agency earmarks a certain amount (say 15%) of a research grant towards OA fees, it would pay for research just once. The OA model has been successful and excellent OA journals now exist. The model has been widely adopted by European governments and there is little doubt that India should follow this path, because it is the future.
Now for the flip side. The UGC regulatory provisions for appointment and accreditation especially in smaller colleges and universities in the country have led to the disgraceful phenomenon of predatory journals that adopt a perverted version of OA. These journals more or less publish any submitted paper without the usual protocols like screening, refereeing, revising and editing. Predatory journals are also able to fix IFs through fake citations. These dubious practices exploit the desperation of researchers who have found this loophole in the UGC regulations to attain eligibility for appointments, promotions and accreditations through a certain number of points to be accrued from publications. Bribe and be published seems to be the norm, as a consequence. Regrettably, India heads the list of countries in terms of the number of predatory journals published (64%) and the number of authors publishing in these journals (11%). According to the Nature Index ( 2014), a large percentage of research articles in India are being published in predatory journals defined as ‘entities that prioritize self-interest at the expense of scholarship and are characterized by false or misleading information, deviation from best editorial/publication practices, lack of transparency, and/or use of aggressive and indiscriminate solicitation practices’. This is a disgrace to not just individuals but their employers and institutions. Retraction Watch is full of papers from Indian academics, proving that the quality of research and publication is dubious, at best.
The UGC’s Consortium for Academic Research and Ethics (CARE) promotes academic integrity and publication ethics, and aims to improve the quality of research in Indian universities. The CARE initiative to clean up research publications in India focuses on predatory publishers/journals. It has done a good job in weeding out many suspect publications. The repeated public notices, gazette notifications and circulars to institutions are sensitizing researchers to the dangers of plagiarism/self-plagiarism, publishing in predatory journals and unethical publishing practices. While all this is welcome, more needs to be done and the benchmark for research evaluation needs to be continuously raised.
The UGC has to make academics and students familiar with research methodology. Publications arise from research. If the research is poor, the outputs will naturally be poor. UGC needs to be strict about evaluation of the quality of research publications, and not just compute numbers.   This also means being vigilant about the quality of research supervision. How research guidance is undertaken today must be rethought even more so in the fund-starved post-COVID dispensation in which we now find ourselves.
The golden mean would be a balance between quantitative and qualitative evaluation. The former could constitute a lower threshold and establish the minimum eligibility for an entry-level appointment or a preliminary/early career award. The latter should be the upper bound, directed at subsequent career advancement (promotions, higher posts), and seek to establish excellence and leadership. But implementation of both these yardsticks needs a high measure of honesty and integrity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>fubar</name></author><category term="education" /><summary type="html">Nice thoughts on the current situation of research evaluation worldwide as well as in the country</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thoracic breathing and tools for becoming awareful</title><link href="/2020/07/08/YogaKshema-thoracic-breathing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thoracic breathing and tools for becoming awareful" /><published>2020-07-08T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-07-08T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/2020/07/08/YogaKshema-thoracic-breathing</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/07/08/YogaKshema-thoracic-breathing.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;practice&quot;&gt;Practice&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stretching exercises to open up the chest and back muscles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thoracic breathing by putting left hand on the abdomen and right hand on the chest. Contrary to abdominal breathing, ensure while inhaling or exhaling, only the chest moves while the abdomen is stationary.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Close the eyes and sequentially focus on each body part from bottom to top. These enables becoming aware of the body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;theory&quot;&gt;Theory&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>fubar</name></author><category term="yoga" /><summary type="html">The next level of breathing is introduced. Followed by method to become aware of the body</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">You are not mind</title><link href="/2020/07/07/YogaKshema-you-are-not-mind.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="You are not mind" /><published>2020-07-07T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-07-07T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/2020/07/07/YogaKshema-you-are-not-mind</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/07/07/YogaKshema-you-are-not-mind.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;practice&quot;&gt;practice&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Close the eyes and focus on a relatively large and stationary object like a building, temple. Try to focus on the object for 2 min&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;theory&quot;&gt;Theory&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The meditator needs to make a clear distinction between the mind and himself in order to progress in the practice of meditation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The meditator needs to realize slowly that s/he is not the mind but &lt;strong&gt;s/he is the witness to the mind&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;story&quot;&gt;Story&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you feel lockdown is unbearable, take inspiration from the great personality Nelson Mandela. Nelson Mandela was imprisoned for 21 years with 19 years of gruelling solitary confinement during apartheid regime of South Africa. Within this period, he suffered loss of his mother and his son. Yet persevered this struggle and later became the first president of democratic South Africa from 1994 to 1999.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=X4AxpLHHnDY&quot;&gt;Yoga Kshema Lesson 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>fubar</name></author><category term="yoga" /><summary type="html">The meditator needs to make a clear distinction between the mind and himself in order to progress in the practice of meditation</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Abdominal breathing and the state of the mind</title><link href="/2020/07/06/YogaKshema-the-state-of-mind.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Abdominal breathing and the state of the mind" /><published>2020-07-06T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-07-06T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/2020/07/06/YogaKshema-the-state-of-mind</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/07/06/YogaKshema-the-state-of-mind.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;practice&quot;&gt;Practice&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Basic stretching exercises&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Abdominal breathing by putting left hand on the abdomen and right hand on the chest. Ensure while inhaling or exhaling, only the abdomen moves while the chest is stationary.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Close the eyes and focus on a relatively large and stationary object like a building, temple. Try to focus on the object for 2 min&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;theory&quot;&gt;Theory&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are four states of mind&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;क्षिप्त अवस्था unable to focus at all&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;विक्षिप्त अवस्था state of mind oscillates between focus and defocus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;मूढ़ अवस्था  A drowsy state of mind&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;एकाग्रतः अवस्था desired state of mind where mind can focus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b0k-uI1rtCA&amp;amp;t=23s&quot;&gt;Yoga Kshema Lesson 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>fubar</name></author><category term="yoga" /><summary type="html">The meditator is introduced to the simplest breathing technique, followed by exposition of four different states of mind during meditation</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thoughts on education by thinkers</title><link href="/2020/07/02/On-Education.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thoughts on education by thinkers" /><published>2020-07-02T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-07-02T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/2020/07/02/On-Education</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/07/02/On-Education.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;swami-vivekananda&quot;&gt;Swami Vivekananda&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the draft of National Education Policy 2019,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;According to Swami Vivekananda,
“Education is not the amount of information that we put into your brain and
runs riot there, undigested, all your life. We must have life-building, man-making, character-making assimilation of ideas. If you have assimilated five ideas and made them your life and character, you have more education than any man who has got by heart a whole library. If education is identical with information, the libraries are the greatest sages of the world and encyclopedia are the greatest Rishis”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>fubar</name></author><category term="education" /><summary type="html">We have listed some thoughts by eminent leaders on the concept of education</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Properties of conventional materials encountered in spintronics</title><link href="/2020/06/29/Conventional-materials-in-spintronics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Properties of conventional materials encountered in spintronics" /><published>2020-06-29T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-06-29T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/2020/06/29/Conventional-materials-in-spintronics</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/06/29/Conventional-materials-in-spintronics.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;metals&quot;&gt;metals&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bass, J. &amp;amp; Pratt, W. P. Jr. Spin-diffusion lengths in metals and alloys, and spin-flipping at metal/metal interfaces: an experimentalist’s critical review. J. Phys. Condens. Matter 19, 183201 (2007)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;yig&quot;&gt;YIG&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spin diffusion length is in few centimeters&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Schneider, T. et al. Realization of spin-wave logic gates. Appl. Phys. Lett. 92, 022505 (2008).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>fubar</name></author><category term="physics" /><summary type="html">We have listed the properties of the usually encountered materials in spintronics ranging from the transition metals and their alloys to the novel materials like YIG opening new vistas in spintronics like magnonics</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reviews of spintronics</title><link href="/2020/06/29/Reviews-of-spintronics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reviews of spintronics" /><published>2020-06-29T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-06-29T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/2020/06/29/Reviews-of-spintronics</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/06/29/Reviews-of-spintronics.html">&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Title&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Author(s)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Journal&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2019&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Current-induced spin-orbit torques in ferromagnetic and antiferromagnetic systems&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Manchon, A.; Železný, J.; Miron, I. M.; Jungwirth, T.; Sinova, J.; Thiaville, A.; Garello, K.; Gambardella, P.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reviews of Modern Physics&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2017&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Magnetic skyrmions: advances in physics and potential applications&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Fert, Albert; Reyren, Nicolas; Cros, Vincent&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Nature Reviews Materials&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2017&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Interface Induced Phenonmena in Magnetism&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hellman, Frances; Hoffmann, Axel; Beach, Geoffrey S D; Fullerton, Eric E; Macdonald, Allan H; Ralph, Daniel C&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reviews of Modern Physics&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2017&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Perpendicular magnetic anisotropy at transition metal/oxide interfaces and applications&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Dieny, B.; Chshiev, M.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reviews of Modern Physics&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2017&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Surprises from the spin Hall effect&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sinova, Jairo; Jungwirth, Tomas&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Physics Today&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2016&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Antiferromagnetic spintronics&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Jungwirth, T.; Marti, X.; Wadley, P.; Wunderlich, J.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Nature Nanotechnology&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2015&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Memory on the racetrack&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Parkin, Stuart; Yang, See Hun&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Nature Nanotechnology&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2015&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Spin Hall effects&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sinova, Jairo; Valenzuela, Sergio O.; Wunderlich, J.; Back, C. H.; Jungwirth, T.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reviews of Modern Physics&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2015&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Magnon spintronics&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Chumak, A. V.; Vasyuchka, V. I.; Serga, A. A.; Hillebrands, B.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Nature Physics&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2014&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Recent advances in nanocontact spin-torque oscillators&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Dumas, Randy K.; Sani, Sohrab R.; Mohseni, S. Majid; Iacocca, Ezio; Pogoryelov, Yevgen; Muduli, Pranaba K.; Chung, Sunjae; Durrenfeld, Philipp; A Akerman, Johan&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;IEEE Transactions on Magnetics&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2012&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Current-induced torques in magnetic materials&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Brataas, Arne; Kent, Andrew D.; Ohno, Hideo&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Nature Materials&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2012&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Spin Hall effect devices&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Jungwirth, Tomas; Wunderlich, Jörg; Olejník, Kamil&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Nature Materials&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ultrathin oxide films and interfaces for electronics and spintronics&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bibes, Manuel; Villegas, Javier E.; Barthélémy, Agnès&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Advances in Physics&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2010&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Anomalous Hall effect&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Nagaosa, Naoto; Sinova, Jairo; Onoda, Shigeki; MacDonald, a. H&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ong, N P&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2010&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ten years of spin hall effect&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;G. Vignale&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Journal of Superconductivity and Novel Magnetism&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2008&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Device implications of spin-transfer torques&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Katine, J. a.; Fullerton, Eric E.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Journal of Magnetism and Magnetic Materials&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2008&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Micro-brillouin light scattering spectroscopy of magnetic nanostructures&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Demokritov, Sergej O.; Demidov, Vladislav E.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;IEEE Transactions on Magnetics (Advances in Magnetics)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2007&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The transition from longitudinal to perpendicular recording&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Richter, H J&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Journal of Physics D: Applied Physics(Topical Review)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2007&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The emergence of spin electronics in data storage&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Chappert, Claude; Fert, Albert; Dau, Frédéric Nguyen Van&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Nature Materials(Review Articles Insight)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2007&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Spin-diffusion lengths in metals and alloys, and spin-flipping at metal/metal interfaces: An experimentalist’s critical review&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bass, Jack; Pratt, William P.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Journal of Physics Condensed Matter (Topical Review)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2007&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Invited article: Vector and Bragg Magneto-optical Kerr effect for the analysis of nanostructured magnetic arrays&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Westphalen, A.; Lee, M. S.; Remhof, A.; Zabel, H.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Review of Scientific Instruments (Invited Article)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2006&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Spin–orbit Driven Physics at Surfaces&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Heide, M; Bihlmayer, G&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://psi-k.net/&quot;&gt;Newsletter of the Psi-K&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2005&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Spin-polarised currents and magnetic domain walls&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Marrows, C. H.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Advances in Physics&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2004&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Current-driven excitations in magnetic multilayers: A brief review&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Bass, J; Urazhdin, S; Birge, Norman O; Pratt, W P&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Physica Status Solidi (A) Applied Research&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2004&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Spintronics: Fundamentals and applications&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Žutić, Igor; Fabian, Jaroslav; Sarma, S. Das&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reviews of Modern Physics&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2001&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Spintronics: A spin-based electronics vision for the future&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Wolf, S. A.; Awschalom, D. D.; Buhrman, R. A.; Daughton, J. M.; Von Molnár, S.; Roukes, M. L.; Chtchelkanova, A. Y.; Treger, D. M.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Science&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1999&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Recent advances in the recording physics of thin-film media&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Richter, Hans Jürgen&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Journal of Physics D: Applied Physics&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1998&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ferromagnetic resonance of ultrathin metallic layers&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Farle, Michael&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reg. Prog. Phys.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1996&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Magnetic anisotropy in metallic multilayers&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Johnson, M T; Bloemen, P J H; Broeder, F J a Den; Vries, J J De&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reports on Progress in Physics&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1998&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Giant magnetoresistance in spin-valve multilayers&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Dieny, B.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Journal of Magnetism and Magnetic Materials&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1989&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Point-contact spectroscopy&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;M, Duif A; M, Jansen A G; P, Wyder&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Journal of Physics: Condensed Matter&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1980&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Dynamic properties of magnetic domain walls and magnetic bubbles&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Leeuw, F H de; Doel, R van den; Enz, U.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reports on Progress in Physics&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1975&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Anisotropic Magnetoresistance&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;McGuire, T R; Potter, R I&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;IEEE transaction on magnetics&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1968&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Magnetic anisotropy in flat ferromagnetic films: A review&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Wilts, C. H.; Humphrey, F. B.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Journal of Applied Physics&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;tutorials&quot;&gt;Tutorials&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Title&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Author(s)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Lectures given at&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2015&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Introduction to spin torques and spin-orbit torques in metal layers&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Gambardella, Pietro&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://intermag.mat.ethz.ch/publications/talks.html&quot;&gt;at ETH Zurich&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2013&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Spintronics research at Cornell&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Liu, Luqiao; Pai, Chi-Feng; Mellnik, Alex; Heron, J.; Grab, J. L.; Lee, O. J.; Li, Y.; Minton, P. J.; Stiehl, G.; Tseng, H. W.; Buhrman, Bob; Ralph, Dan; Richardella, Anthony ; Lee, Joon Sue; Samarth, Nitin&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://online.kitp.ucsb.edu/online/spintronics13/ralph/pdf/Ralph_Spintronics13_KITP.pdf&quot;&gt;at Cornell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;roadmap&quot;&gt;Roadmap&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Title&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Author(s)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Journal&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2017&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Digital Storage and Memory Technology ( Part 1 )&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Coughlin, Tom; Hoyt, Roger; Handy, Jim&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;IEEE&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2017&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The 2017 Magnetism Roadmap&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Sander, D.; Valenzuela, S. O.; Makarov, D.; Marrows, C. H.; Fullerton, E. E.; Fischer, P.; McCord, J.; Vavassori, P.; Mangin, S.; Pirro, P.; Hillebrands, B.; Kent, A. D.; Jungwirth, T.; Gutfleisch, O.; Kim, C. G.; Berger, A.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Journal of Physics D: Applied Physics&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;related-reviews&quot;&gt;Related Reviews&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Title&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Author(s)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Journal&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2010&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Berry phase effects on electronic properties&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Xiao, Di; Chang, Ming Che; Niu, Qian&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reviews of Modern Physics&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2008&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Spin transfer torques&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ralph, D. C.; Stiles, M. D.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Journal of Magnetism and Magnetic Materials&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1987&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The interaction of water with solid surfaces: Fundamental aspects&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thiel, Patricia a.; Madey, Theodore E.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Surface Science Reports&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1984&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Nucleation and growth of thin films: recent progress&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Venables, J.a.; G.D.T., Spiller; Hanbucken, M.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reports on Progress in Physics&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1949&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Physical theory of ferromagnetic domains&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Kittel, Charles&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reviews of Modern Physics&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;related-tutorials&quot;&gt;Related Tutorials&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Title&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Author(s)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Lectures given at&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Basic Principles of X-ray Reflectivity in Thin Films&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Jimenez-Villacorta, Felix&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eng.uc.edu/~beaucag/Classes/Characterization/ReflectivityLab/NorthEastern%20University%20Basic%20Principles%20of%20X-ray%20Reflectivity%20in%20Thin%20Films%20-%20Felix%20Jimenez-Villacorta%20%5BCompatibility%20Mode%5D.pdf&quot;&gt;at NorthEastern University&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;X-ray diffraction techniques for thin films&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Konya, Takayuki&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://homepage.ntu.edu.tw/~kcyuan/form/For-Rigaku-Upload_thinfilm.pdf&quot;&gt;at NTU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content><author><name>fubar</name></author><category term="physics" /><summary type="html">A chronological list of spintronics review articles with an attempt to create a mind map between the articles</summary></entry></feed>